<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-31T15:22:36+00:00</updated><id>https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/feed.xml</id><title type="html">LaBackDoor</title><subtitle>An engaging 1-3 sentence description of your lab.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">AI Threat Hunting Lab: Week 2 - Network Deep Dive</title><link href="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/2025/10/28/ai-threat-hunting-lab-week-2-network-deep-dive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI Threat Hunting Lab: Week 2 - Network Deep Dive" /><published>2025-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/2025/10/28/ai-threat-hunting-lab-week-2-network-deep-dive</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/2025/10/28/ai-threat-hunting-lab-week-2-network-deep-dive.html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back to the AI Threat Hunting Lab build! As promised in last week’s update, this post is a technical deep dive into the core components, configurations, and software used to get the network backbone online.</p>

<p>If you’re looking to replicate this setup, this post will serve as your guide.</p>

<p><img src="/images/ai_sec_lab_week2_diagram.png" alt="week_2_updated_diagram" /></p>

<h2 id="part-1-the-software-stack-the-isos">Part 1: The Software Stack (The ISOs)</h2>

<p>First, let’s cover the “building blocks.” All components are running as virtual machines, and the first step was to download the necessary ISO files.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>pfSense (Firewall/Router):</strong> This is the heart of our network, managing all routing, segmentation, and firewall rules.
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Download:</strong> <a href="https://www.pfsense.org/download/">https://www.pfsense.org/download/</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Kali Linux (Attacker):</strong> Our dedicated offensive machine.
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Download:</strong> <a href="https://www.kali.org/get-kali/#kali-installer-images">https://www.kali.org/get-kali/#kali-installer-images</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Ubuntu Desktop (Client):</strong> Our “victim” or standard user endpoint.
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Download:</strong> <a href="https://ubuntu.com/download/desktop">https://ubuntu.com/download/desktop</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Splunk Free (SIEM):</strong> The core of our visibility and monitoring. We are using the free license.
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Download:</strong> <a href="https://help.splunk.com/en/splunk-enterprise/administer/admin-manual/9.4/configure-splunk-licenses/about-splunk-free">Splunk Free Download Page</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="part-2-pfsense-configuration-deep-dive">Part 2: pfSense Configuration Deep Dive</h2>

<p>Getting pfSense configured correctly is the most critical part of this foundation. As shown in last week’s diagram, we have a Management (MGMT) network (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.1/24</code>) and an Corporate Network (Corp) network (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.2.1/24</code>). I also created a DMZ network for AI services.</p>

<p>Here are the exact configurations from my lab setup.</p>

<h3 id="interface-configuration">Interface Configuration</h3>

<p>Here is the breakdown of the virtual interfaces assigned in pfSense.</p>

<p><img src="/images/pfsense_config.jpeg" alt="PFSence Configuration" /></p>

<h3 id="firewall-rules">Firewall Rules</h3>

<p>Rules are key to segmenting our lab. The goal is to allow the MGMT network to access everything, but prevent the Corp and DMZ network from directly accessing the MGMT network.</p>

<p><strong>WAN Rules:</strong></p>

<p><img src="/images/wan_rules.png" alt="WAN Rules" /></p>

<p><strong>CORP Rules:</strong></p>

<p><img src="/images/corp_rules.png" alt="Corp Rules" /></p>

<p><strong>DMZ Rules:</strong></p>

<p><img src="/images/dmz_rules.png" alt="DMZ Rules" /></p>

<p><strong>MGMT Rules:</strong></p>

<p><img src="/images/mgnt_rules.png" alt="Management Rules" /></p>

<h3 id="nat-rules">NAT Rules</h3>

<p><img src="/images/nat_rules.png" alt="NAT Rules" /></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="part-3-splunk-installation">Part 3: Splunk Installation</h2>

<p>With the network foundation built, the next step was setting up our SIEM. I installed this on an Ubuntu VM with the static IP of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.100</code> (on the MGMT network).</p>

<p>The installation process is very straightforward. I followed this excellent step-by-step guide:</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>**Guide:** [Installing Splunk Enterprise on Ubuntu: Step-by-Step Guide</td>
      <td>by Daniel Opara</td>
      <td>Medium](https://medium.com/@daniel.opara/installing-splunk-enterprise-on-ubuntu-step-by-step-guide-8d1b168a306)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>After installation, the next step (which I’ll detail later) is to configure the Splunk Universal Forwarder.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next</h2>

<p>That’s all for this technical breakdown! With the network configured and our SIEM online, the lab is truly ready.</p>

<p>The next phase, as mentioned last week, is to begin deploying the AI/LLM components into the DMZ. Stay tuned!</p>]]></content><author><name>banny orojo</name></author><category term="ai-security" /><category term="threat-hunting" /><category term="homelab" /><category term="devsecops" /><category term="pfsense" /><category term="splunk" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome back to the AI Threat Hunting Lab build! As promised in last week’s update, this post is a technical deep dive into the core components, configurations, and software used to get the network backbone online.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/images/ai_sec_lab_week2_diagram.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/images/ai_sec_lab_week2_diagram.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">AI Threat Hunting Lab: Week 1 Progress - Core Network &amp;amp; Visibility Online</title><link href="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/2025/10/21/ai-threat-hunting-lab-core-network-online.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI Threat Hunting Lab: Week 1 Progress - Core Network &amp;amp; Visibility Online" /><published>2025-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/2025/10/21/ai-threat-hunting-lab-core-network-online</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/2025/10/21/ai-threat-hunting-lab-core-network-online.html"><![CDATA[<p>A quick update on the AI Threat Hunting Lab! The core network backbone is now complete, featuring a Kali attacker, an Ubuntu client, pfSense for routing, and Splunk for centralized visibility.
Hello everyone, and welcome back! Following my initial post, I’ve decided to switch this tracking journey to a <strong>weekly update</strong> to better capture the rapid progress of building out the AI Threat Hunting Lab.</p>

<p>I’m happy to report that the <strong>network backbone</strong> is now fully operational! This initial phase was crucial for establishing the foundational security and visibility layers before we dive into the machine learning components. This is the solid footing we need.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-core-infrastructure-is-online">The Core Infrastructure is Online</h2>

<p>As you can see in the provided diagram, the environment is now configured, establishing the <strong>Untrusted Network / Internet</strong> and the <strong>Management Network</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="../images/ai_sec_lab_week1.png" alt="AI Threat Hunting Lab Diagram: Backbone Network" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>pfSense (192.168.1.1):</strong> This acts as our crucial network boundary, firewall, and router, securely connecting the attacker/client zone (10.100.1.1/24) to the management zone (192.168.1.1/24).</li>
  <li><strong>Attacker/Client Endpoints (Kali &amp; Ubuntu):</strong> We have <strong>Kali Linux</strong> (10.100.1.20) as the dedicated attacker machine and an <strong>Ubuntu Client</strong> (10.100.1.30) to simulate a standard user endpoint—perfect for practicing penetration testing and defense scenarios against our future AI application.</li>
  <li><strong>Splunk (192.168.1.10):</strong> The centerpiece of our visibility strategy is now online. Splunk is collecting logs from all relevant endpoints, giving us the centralized monitoring needed to analyze and hunt for threats from the attacker environment.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="whats-next-the-ai-layer">What’s Next: The AI Layer</h2>

<p>With the traditional security foundation set, the next phase will be the most exciting—integrating the <strong>AI/LLM components</strong>.</p>

<p>The bottom section of the diagram—the <strong>LiteLLM Gateway</strong>, <strong>Local LLM Inference Server</strong>, <strong>MCP</strong>, and <strong>Vector Database</strong>—represents the core architecture for our <em>target application</em> we will be securing. The coming weeks will be spent deciding on the specific software/models for these roles and getting them wired into the network.</p>

<p>This was a short but important update. The lab has a heartbeat! Stay tuned for next week as we start configuring the first AI component.</p>]]></content><author><name>banny orojo</name></author><category term="ai-security" /><category term="threat-hunting" /><category term="homelab" /><category term="devsecops" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A quick update on the AI Threat Hunting Lab! The core network backbone is now complete, featuring a Kali attacker, an Ubuntu client, pfSense for routing, and Splunk for centralized visibility. Hello everyone, and welcome back! Following my initial post, I’ve decided to switch this tracking journey to a weekly update to better capture the rapid progress of building out the AI Threat Hunting Lab.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/images/ai_sec_lab_week1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/images/ai_sec_lab_week1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Starting the Journey to AI Security Engineering</title><link href="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/2025/10/14/The-Journey-to-AI-Security-Engineering.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starting the Journey to AI Security Engineering" /><published>2025-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-31T15:09:36+00:00</updated><id>https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/2025/10/14/The-Journey-to-AI-Security-Engineering</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/2025/10/14/The-Journey-to-AI-Security-Engineering.html"><![CDATA[<p>As a PhD student with a deep background in both AI and traditional security, I’m pivoting my focus to the practical, industry-driven field of <strong>AI Security Engineering</strong>. This post marks the beginning of my tracking journey, outlining the core distinction of this new discipline and my immediate plan.
This blog will serve as a bi-weekly tracker for my learning and practical application in the emerging domain of <strong>AI Security Engineering</strong>. Given my foundational expertise in both AI and traditional Security, my focus here is on understanding where the practical industry implementation and threat modeling are heading.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="ai-security-engineer-vs-traditional-security-engineer">AI Security Engineer vs. Traditional Security Engineer</h2>

<p>The role of a <strong>Traditional Security Engineer</strong> is fundamentally about securing the environment around the application: the network, the operating system, the data layer, and the established code base (e.g., against OWASP Top 10). The threat landscape, while evolving, is relatively well-defined.</p>

<p>The <strong>AI Security Engineer</strong> takes a distinct step forward, focusing on securing the <strong>Machine Learning (ML) lifecycle itself</strong>—the data, the model, and the deployment pipeline (MLOps). While traditional security protects the infrastructure <em>hosting</em> the model, AI Security protects the model’s <strong>integrity, confidentiality, and availability</strong> from <em>model-specific attacks</em>.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">Focus Area</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Traditional Security Engineering</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">AI Security Engineering</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">**Primary Target**</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Networks, Endpoints, Applications, Databases</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Training Data, ML Model Artifacts, MLOps Pipelines</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">**Core Threat Model**</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Exploits, Vulnerabilities, Misconfigurations</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">**Adversarial Attacks** (Evasion, Poisoning), **Privacy Attacks** (Model Inversion, Membership Inference), **Prompt Injection** (for LLMs)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">**Goal**</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">CIA Triad of Infrastructure/Data</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Robustness and Trustworthiness of the ML System</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The discipline requires layering new ML-centric defenses over a robust foundation of cloud and application security.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="resource-plan--progress-tracker">Resource Plan &amp; Progress Tracker</h2>

<p>My goal is to dedicate a focused effort to bridge the theoretical knowledge gap with industry practices, especially since most deployments will be cloud-native.</p>

<h3 id="-core-reading">📚 Core Reading</h3>

<p>I will be extracting practical insights from the following texts:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The Developer’s Playbook for Large Language Model Security</li>
  <li>Adversarial AI Attacks, Mitigations, and Defense Strategies</li>
  <li>Practicing Trustworthy Machine Learning</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="-courses--certifications">🎓 Courses &amp; Certifications</h3>

<p>I plan to examine the curriculum and key takeaways from these industry-recognized programs:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Certified AI Security Professional - AI Security Certification - Practical DevSecOps
* AI security fundamentals - Training | Microsoft Learn</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="-daily-focus-the-mlops-foundation">🎥 Daily Focus: The MLOps Foundation</h3>

<p>To ensure I understand the operational context of AI deployment, I am dedicating <strong>2 hours a day</strong> to mastering the production lifecycle. My starting point is a deep dive into AWS deployment:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Resource:</strong> <strong>AWS Cloud Complete Bootcamp Course</strong> by Jeff Hale</li>
  <li><strong>Link:</strong> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zA8guDqfv40">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zA8guDqfv40</a></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>Looking forward to posting my first progress update / or lab deployment in two weeks!</p>]]></content><author><name>Banny Orojo</name></author><category term="ai-security" /><category term="devsecops" /><category term="llm-security" /><category term="mlops" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As a PhD student with a deep background in both AI and traditional security, I’m pivoting my focus to the practical, industry-driven field of AI Security Engineering. This post marks the beginning of my tracking journey, outlining the core distinction of this new discipline and my immediate plan. This blog will serve as a bi-weekly tracker for my learning and practical application in the emerging domain of AI Security Engineering. Given my foundational expertise in both AI and traditional Security, my focus here is on understanding where the practical industry implementation and threat modeling are heading.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/images/security-data-model.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://labackdoor.github.io/lab-website/images/security-data-model.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>